hey marjenka hi guy it's good to see you
again it's good to be seen and welcome
everybody who's watching the this is
part three of you could say kind of the
second version or the continuing version
of our conversations on attachment
theory and how it relates to circling
and we did a video about a year ago that
was about an hour long and then you've
been doing a lot of research and
specifically specifically we're gonna be
using quotes and have been using quotes
out of a particular book that you're
going to talk more about and and
beginning to have a dialogue between the
experience that you've had with me
through circling oh you've really found
that like something that's happening in
circling points to a lot of the things
that have been researched and documented
around attachment theory and that so so
you've been in a certain sense you've
been standing between like a foot in
both worlds and been in this oh my god
experience you know this is actually
we're practicing this stuff encircling
and you've had quite a fire and a fury
almost I would say an intellectual fury
to really make that connection and so
I've just really appreciated that about
you I've just always appreciated about
that you know that you are permeable to
be infected with really brilliant ideas
and want to continually explore them and
and feel moved like no one's asking you
to do this right you could just have
your practice and live your life
but there's something in you that is
interested in this and wants to write
articles and publish them and do videos
with me and post them on Facebook and
have a dialogue going on no one's asking
you to do this this is really coming
from someplace in your own heart and I
just want to acknowledge that in you
that this is really generous of you to
to do
and to provide this because I don't no
one else is doing this in the world but
the curse for you so I feel blessed to
be you know I just feel blessed to be in
your life and to be impacted by you as I
have and to deepen deepen these
distinctions and something that's that's
important to you and to me and so many
people that we that we know and love and
also people that that we would know and
love if we knew you and I just curious I
I'd love to I'd love to actually ask you
are you good about like what is what is
it been like you know for you writing
researching and writing and in preparing
the quotes and being on camera and
having this interview and like what's
what's the experience this mean to you
what's it like what's it been like mmm
yeah I I appreciate that because it
feels like we're bringing circling
directly a little bit into this
interview and so as you've been talking
I just felt this dropping away of all
the things I want to talk about today
and just watching you reflect me back to
me and just I felt this expansion
happening or just the settling I guess I
was receiving what you were saying I was
um I guess I'm there aren't really words
to describe what it was just happening
while I was listening to you well I know
one of the things that I said was you
know I mentioned the fire that you have
there's something speaking to you that
you that you feel compelled to write
about to get over fears and anxieties
about you know being seen in the public
and in front of cameras you know there's
some sacrificing a lot of your own
comfort in your own time
I really am that's true I mean I'm
starting to really look forward to these
videos and I'm enjoying them but they
you know as we keep talking about
there's also a lot of nervous excitement
and
you're helping me deepen into presents
before we start I really appreciate that
it's actually been mixed it's I've been
consistently the way I write is I know I
don't do it in an effective way I do it
where I just create tons of documents I
make a big mess and then I spend all my
time trying to organize it and in that
process is how I was learning this book
and and there were times weeks and
months maybe where I wasn't able to get
back in where I felt kicked out in the
last year and but recently when my
brother died I I had another period
where I I had just been inspired up
until he suddenly died and then I
couldn't touch it for a month so that
was in November and then and then in
descend of December and this month there
were a few days where I really struggled
with it I felt lost and confused and you
know it was overwhelming I thought oh my
god I've been doing this for a year and
I'm still not ready to have these
interviews and then all of a sudden I
had a breakthrough it started coming
together and I just you know I just said
I got to stop messing around let's just
do something already so so there's
organized as I could get it's the last
couple of weeks and and the more I sit
with it they're starting to be new
dimensions that I'm seeing for example I
want to mention that so as I'm seeing
the way circling is paralleling
attachment theory in psychotherapy in a
lot of ways that so many people are also
doing this they're doing parts of this
and I'm just seeing they're such an
inherent drive to towards I think so
many people are naturally discovering
the like the portals to secure
attachment without knowing using that
lens and so one thing I'm wanting is to
you know just bring the lens to more and
more
people even if they've heard of it to
make it more interesting because often I
think I think what really makes a
difference is when when there's an equal
focus on subjectivity and inner
subjectivity and so psychotherapy can
often focus more on the intrapsychic and
a little bit on the inner subjective but
I'm so people are okay interest I kick
for interest for uh
yeah interest psychic like inside yeah
yourself that's like subjectivity and
then inter subjective inter subjective
is the we face between the two of us the
relationship and one part that we're
gonna get to in a couple or two or three
segments is about how mindfulness works
in attachment when I'm getting about it
how it works an attachment healing and
that's part of the stance towards
experience the way Walland describes it
this book I don't think we've mentioned
it yet attachment healing in
psychotherapy by David Wallen and so
many many it's an incredibly long
tradition and and elaborate and complex
of mindfulness in fact I'm following
this free online mindfulness summit
right now through sounds true it's
available to you you can watch every day
presence that's a week or next week but
or you can buy it for $200 it's
fascinating thirty two presenters I
think and so there's so much to say
about mindfulness but having read this
book what I'm getting is there might be
missing for those that are suffering in
relationship even when you meditate and
you study deep deeply the field of
mindfulness mentalization which we'll
get to next time is the psychological
dimension and being able to see see the
states that you're in and and again I
want to emphasize attachment theory is
talking about relationship so it's
really emphasizing I think the the
[Music]
the interdependence of being securely
attached rather than the independence of
being avoidant lis attached that the
attachment for the child creates a field
that their body our bodies learn how to
regulate how to feel and what predicts
attachment is the degree to which what
is allowed what experience is allowed
and what is not allowed what can be felt
what cannot be felt because it's
imperative that there is this attachment
and so the child will like I said last
time I think we'll put aside
unconsciously the things that don't fit
with the parent and but as adults when
we get to adulthood then I think that
that is a primary way of recovering like
I was saying before the hourglass theory
and I didn't get an actual hourglass yet
but I got the next best thing which is
um an image of an hourglass and so let
me talk about the original experience
and secure attachment being the goal and
that it teaches us these capacities how
to be in the world but then when we get
to adulthood if we did not have the
secure base established that we can feed
these capacities in different ways and
then it grows that secure base and so is
it fair to say that basically what
you're saying is that like if you didn't
have it when you were a kid it doesn't
mean that you can't establish it for
yourself now yeah that's what that's
what I'm reading about that's what
Wallen and the many many people you know
an important lens that the therapist has
to wake up parts of themselves I've been
doing that for the last five years you
know with you and with the community
here in Berkeley and I like I haven't
been doing it enough I
want more I need more because I've been
leading the groups and I found that it's
harder for me to really wake up these
edges and myself when I'm also holding
the space and that's been an ongoing
dialogue as you know and in fact I
wanted to mention one other part I was
thinking of Alexis Alexis Shepherd and I
was thinking how how well she she does
these three parts where she she shares
her direct experience um like subjective
experience she's in the interaction she
reflects she is she's a tuning with the
others in the group and she's holding
the space and I just really see her do
those three things really well yes she's
quite exceptional at those three dreams
she's like almost I would almost say
she's almost kind of like the archetype
of mother and some in some respects yeah
I think that's a good way to put it
lieblick is a mother rights except when
I think about a mother and mother logs a
child like and it's not just like an
altruistic act no she's enjoying the
experience of loving child I my my
girlfriend's sister just had a baby and
I'm watching I'm watching this pure
potential of that the family and
watching the grad fit this new
grandmother basically look at this child
and then just you could just list going
through every cell of her body the
mother and of breanne when they see the
child it's almost it's as if I was I was
I was on vacation and and they were they
they that her family the child was
coming in like a day later and I was
taking a nap downstairs and I just had
just started to wake up as the baby was
coming in and for some reason I was I
just listen tonight and it and I thought
and instead of imagine like what if what
if I imagine that baby Jesus was coming
or baby Buddha was coming and I listened
to the way everyone was responding
upstairs and it was exactly it would
have totally fit it was the same kind of
thing it's like oh my god the second
coming or the or the most beautiful
thing in the world and watching the
energy that this is what I think
children give back because there are a
lot of work there are a lot of work so I
think the payback for having kids is
that we get we get a direct intimation
of what we're like or I have a direct a
direct intimation of the pure potential
that a human being is because when you
think about what one single human being
is capable of it is profound
to be with an infant right it's profound
to be with an infant and it seems the
biological response to that like the
spiritual response to that but it's
deeply rooted in the body because you
can feel the whole family mmm
gather around as if a bright pure light
was coming into being proximity to the
attachment figures serve literally to
regulate the internal functioning of the
infant's body and evidence suggests that
the quality of the attachment
relationship secure or insecure
influences how the infant's developing
physiology shapes the body's self
responsiveness to experience so that
phrase is one part we want to take away
their the the relationship influences
the body's self responsiveness to
experience through the relationship and
then you can read that that next
sentence we definitely job for example D
the secure infant sensitively responsive
mothers have a higher threshold for the
activation of physiological stress
responses and the insecure offspring of
dismissing preoccupied and especially
resolved mothers and so that phrase the
higher threshold or the activation of
physiological stress responses that is
about effect regulation you know we feel
emotion emotion is a primary means of us
knowing what's important to us what we
care about right those are two phrases
that you focus on encircling but if the
energy of the emotion of the stress if
there's a stress response is too much
because of it it wasn't regulated early
on in relationship that somebody you
know people have different responses but
generally if somebody's avoidant ly
attached they shut it down and withdraw
to manage the stress response or if
they're anxious it just comes forward
more for example of not being able to
keep feeling the experience like fix it
over here can you help me fix this you
know so those as children and adults
those could be two ways of responding to
it not not having not integrating the
physiological stress response through a
relationship
it isn't that like I remember when I had
Forrest my son he was watching watching
the pattern of just how he was
especially when it was just an infant
right he's kind of like an
undifferentiated blob right that slowly
someone started to be there which was
fascinating to me about we can talk
about that I think in objects relations
theory they called it hatching you know
someone's behind the eyes I can't quite
explain that but but it seemed that
being a baby is a series of like is
basically being an undifferentiated
bunch of tubes right where there's a
build up X of excitation and then of
like say I need I'm hungry or I need to
poop or I need to suck on a nipple or
whatever it is right and it would build
up as a as a of excitation and then the
mother or me or somebody
the caregiver would come and then meet
the need and there was this release and
relaxation of excitation and it just
seemed to have this kind of movement of
excitation build up and release
excitation build up in a release so I'm
how I'm here like that's what I thought
of as you're talking about it so I would
imagine if the mother if that if that
was if there was a buildup of excitation
instead of I need being mad instead it
was like they got the nipple but it was
filled with like the mother's
insecurities about whether or not she
knows how to do it or she's a good
mother
or if Shh he got met with the Blake like
effective disdain or frustration or some
version other than oh let me meet your
need then that excitation builds up and
then at a certain point you probably
crosses threshold it's right yes yes and
in in that that crossing of threshold
over a number of times starts a pattern
in your nervous system and so this is
one thing that I think there's two parts
that I think that quote was focusing on
that there's overarching concepts to
carry through everything we're talking
about that circling is doing which is we
are practicing emotional attunement
effect attunements and the idea is when
that's happening it's helping the other
to regulate effect so that's one very
important part and just so so we're
clear about some of these technologies
when you mean regulate right when we
self-regulate what what are you actually
referring to well I think that it is the
way you just describe that excitement
emerges in in the system and then we can
feel it first of all because we can be
dissociated from the feelings and we can
just be in thoughts or images or spaced
out many different responses to not
being directly connected to the arise
the rise and fall of energy in the body
and so regulating means that you can
that you have options for how to manage
the energy you couldn't you have enough
ability to say if you're with people
okay hold on I need a minute and just
either you stay there and you breathe or
you say can you go take a walk with me I
mean you have these you know I think
this is part of mentalizing is the
ability to perceive different things
that are happening within you and in
relationship and to be able to choose
options for how to respond so we'll of
course you're getting to that next time
you say when people say you know
encircling a lot of times people say
like to collect a lot more grounded
hearing that yeah look a lot more
centered or more in my body is that like
he could say is like in a certain sense
that's them them feeling self regulated
yeah or when they stop and make it like
they take a deep breath and they just
kind of breathe into the intensity and
make room for the intensity such that
they can like have it versus it having
them or something absolutely and I think
there's a term also a mutual regulation
something like that and so I think
encircling we're off we can often be
doing it mutually and then self
regulating is is I think more where you
feel contained within yourself right and
so there's a way in which regulation can
happen you can integrate and
self-regulate in insults ooh is that
another term like self soothing yeah
sometimes can be part of it regulation
but then there's what you're saying is
that there's the possibility of insecure
attachment bonds we're where we can
couple and relate to each other in such
a way that we can we can regulate each
other and that's that and that's that
that's that's really what we're gonna
get getting at is like the possibility
of relationships ways of interacting
where both of us feel much more enriched
and regulated and centered in our own
experience and I think maybe we should
jump over all this stuff I wish we could
talk about but go to how we listen in
circling because
I think that what I was saying in the
last segment was this is this is where I
take a creative leap right so much of
Wallens every his outline of his book so
much peril easily is paralleling and
what we're doing encircling but in many
ways but then this leap that I'm taking
is that the question of if a surrogate
field a surrogate caregiver a surrogate
secure base a surrogate safe haven is is
created because of the mutual agreements
that we have so that we may not even
know each other but because we know that
we are here to welcome everything we can
welcome to welcome our subjective
experience each other's experience we
know that's what we're trying to do even
when we can't even in moments where we
feel shut down or we feel upset we know
ultimately there's a field that's saying
it's okay we welcome the shutdown you
know that that the most basic agreement
is that we are agreeing to be in
relationship so even if we just
acknowledge I don't know how to do it in
this moment there's still a deeper
intention saying yes I'm willing to find
my way back to relating with you I may
not be with you yeah like I've thrown a
beacon out your language I'm here and
I'm connected to you and I'm gonna find
my way back yeah because I I have this
idea you can tell me what you think but
I've often said this I think if people
if sometimes I'll ask someone are you
willing to be in relationship when
somebody is really something's really
edgy and they're just they seem like
they don't care anymore
you know and I've heard somebody say
once no and I made the decision to stop
the circle I said okay wait if you're
not willing to be in relationship to
these people right now then we need to
pause timeout because to me it was
breaking the agreements and I wonder
what you think about that I think it
depends on the situation it sounds like
it sounds like you know one of the
commitments you could say that we have
is to relationship we're staying
connected and so if the person was in
the person was like nope no more and
they were closed about it right that was
it yeah it was it like they were just
kind of taking care of themselves which
is which is waves actually staying
connected to somebody yes I agree but
there was a way of just kind of climbing
walling it up and good shunning or
something or other ring you they were
saying I was not willing to be affected
by the other basically I'm just not
willing yeah totally yeah that kind of
just breaks the rules of the game that's
what I was yeah
was there another quote he wanted to go
into yeah so there will be a few here so
we'll talk about we'll focus mostly on
listening principles but maybe you can
just talk a little bit first on how you
describe you know when we have a
Thursday night drop encircling night
well you always say it differently what
would you say right now about how we
listen what that's one of the three
agreements encircling that we use right
what would you say so so for me I would
say that like actually it's been
listening in the way that we listen as a
virtue and there's a standard and to
come from encircling I've really caught
that has been the most transformative
that's what's transformed to me through
circling is it's surprisingly so um I
wouldn't I wouldn't have thought that in
advance like well how does listening how
could listening transform you it's like
you're just paying attention right what
I love I I think I'm still I'm still
grokking how how deep listen it goes and
what we mean by listening in this way is
to genuinely listen to another human
being as a genuine human being is a real
human being or as Mark Martin Buber
would say as a genuine I though you were
though in other words you I relate to
you not as a means to an end
but as an end in yourself if you can
feel it like in Gruber talks about it
also as you know he pairs it off he says
you know to be existentially to be human
being is to be a relationship we're
always in relationship with entities and
events and ourselves and other people
and that we comport or the way that our
stance towards that relationship he puts
in two categories one is an i8
relationship and one is danaiah
relationship and he says that both are
spoken is one word and I it and I that
there's always the
I pull and the other pull and he says
like when I relate to you isn't it
I'm not relating to you as an entity
illegitimate meaningful entities in
yourself I'm relating to you as a means
to an end right if you can kind of feel
the I that comes up if I were just a bit
like for example if I were to start to
relate to you as a means to my need to
get to meet my needs to be accepted or
approved up right in some way you kind
of feel the I that forms in relationship
to that versus if I if I meet you and
listen to you and apprehend you as a
though and I really really want to come
in contact with not what I already know
about you but what I don't know about
you right and if you can kind of feel
the respectfulness that comes with being
with a legitimate other you feel the I
that emerges with that right in that in
that in that primordial relational event
I thou so if you think about listening
from that angle listening becomes not
something simply where you just are an
empty head being quiet paying attention
being filled with information right I
think that's the common sense notion of
listening is that like being a good
listener is simply being quiet and
paying attention to what you say like as
if we open you open my head up and you
fill it with words and once it's filled
and you're done talking we close that
and then I process the information and
then I and then I respond back to you in
some way but that's not the that's not
the phenomenological that's not the way
we experience listening right how we
experience listening is there's this way
in which I in listening to you
especially in the I thou sense of the
word genuinely really really listening
to who you are in your full humanity
right is in a certain sense is to is to
listen to you is to open up the way
makes sense
world and through understanding you
through feeling you through being
attuned to you that I go on a ride I'm
willing to go on a ride and here's the
key where I'm willing and open to be
changed and impacted through the
experience of hearing you right I'm I'm
willing to be untouchable I make myself
touchable I make myself being in a
certain sense being affected sometimes
really deeply yeah I think that I think
that listening to so many people open
their hearts and finding out who they
were at the deepest level it's like a
it's like accompanying people and
listening to people that way I have
listened to people that have been so
moving and so courageous and just blown
me away that I that that it's altered
the way that I see reality through the
process of listening to them and that I
would say that that that how you feel
heard is to the degree that you can that
I can communicate to you how I'm being
changed by what you're saying and that's
the experience where people feel deeply
hurt right it's a full embodiment so
there's a component to it where there's
a there's a embodied attunement there's
a kind of a listening body where there's
a porosity right in the stance a I'm
really gonna I'm gonna bring my whole
being right to you and I'm gonna be
attuned to you on a on a primordial
physical and body level you know open
myself up to you at a nonverbal level
right and that is really really
important and in such that the words
that you say already happened with it
arise from a sense of attunement right
as if you had a tone and I had its own
and in listening to you I'm tuning in in
a bodily way
so the to your particular tone right and
out of that animates the conversation
right
and you can feel the tonality of that
change as the conversation happens right
you can feel the relationship and the
tones start to be contributed to both of
us right and that's where you start to
create these really epic beautiful deep
rich connections and conversations where
at a certain point it's really hard to
say that like the two human beings are
the source of the conversation it starts
to feel like the conversation of the
relationship starts degree to people Wow
and those are the kinds of things that
have I think we're people that really
take take a note of circling oh my god
this is really amazing
you mean I could just meet a stranger
and sit down and have that kind of
conversation a way that enriched and
transformed that's what's possible yeah
so one thing I was noting is they're
just at least four different parts that
you describe that are basically
word-for-word you know what
therapists are doing in psychotherapy
but yet there's this way of still
holding oneself back to a degree right
so there's a therapist yeah and the idea
in circle is you're two human beings or
two or more meeting and an equal ground
and so that's the part where I think
circling is an incredible compliment to
attachment therapy because it brings it
gives people the ultimate lesson they
need which is how to be equally in
relationship not just somebody who is
only looking for your best interest
and putting aside their own personal
needs a lot of the time right to show up
it gets infinitely more complex
encircling you can get messy but in the
mess and then the repair is where the
learning and the healing happens also Oh
so you know one thing you were
mentioning was about the the approach to
the other person and you I don't even
think you said this phrase but you were
referring to assuming positive intent or
maybe you did say it and I guess to me
it when weird when we're doing that if
you bring this to any relation adult
relationship you have it's already
creating a mind state where if you're if
you really learn to make that a practice
where you assume positive intent yeah
then you're not leading with that the
you're working that edge from thinking
you're insulting me right or you don't
understand me
it's it's a really complex place right
when you feet when there's this when
there's some things at stake and you
want someone to get you and and if two
people who practice circling together
but you know you're in relationship or
family members but you can bring that
stance of positive intent I think it it
teaches the other that you will assume
the best of me under stress and that
does something I think that just creates
a base to rest into yeah just get
stressed yeah but to find that pathway
of wait what's the deeper something's
hurting here you know what's the deeper
meaning and to just let go of the
expression of it just get to the you
know that's one thing we practice
encircling another and I'll have a quote
for you to read is in we listen for how
things make sense what one more part
should positive intent so like when we
when we practice that that's a committed
thing that we do in circling it's an
intent that we have is is that we say
that like one of the ways we're gonna
listen to each other is really listen
for and assumed positive intent
it doesn't mean liking what the person
says or what they're doing does have
anything to do with approval right right
more like assuming that the person is
doing the best they can
with what they're given yeah and even if
they don't think so
really listening for that and holding
them in that way and what I have found
and I've watched people who have
practiced at that at first it's kind of
like it's a it's a stance they take on
almost like they wear it which is a
start like a coat like kind of a good
sexual thing but then as time goes on
I've watched people literally be able to
perceive the innocence and people right
to actually have that to be to be able
to have that have a limbic felt almost
sensory visceral hit but when somebody's
just being a bastard right screaming at
their face like actually being able to
like deal with the conversation but hold
that person and actually feel the
innocence of that person right and
understand that person as in attuned way
but that's actually possible to develop
and to feel to actually perceive that
spark of light of purity that's within
everybody jet and like just like when
you practice yoga there's asanas
positions that you hold in a certain
sense there are you could say relational
asanas that we hold right and some will
be harder for like like for example that
I've been lifting weights for years so I
hate downward dog
maybe fortress-like the best thing for
me but I hate the yoga instructors I
feel like that they're just like you
know they're st. and there's something
like that because I hate but I you know
I get done with it and then I walk
outside when I'm not thinking about
doing downward dog my natural resting
bit like face is more open and I think
the same is ways when you hold an
intention of seeing the positive intent
and other people and you stretch so as
that person is doing saying that thing
that's like just like your mother said
to you and it's activating everything in
your life you're practicing feeling for
the innocence even as they're burning
you in a certain sense feeling that
right and you
stretch those capacities and in and hold
off on what you maybe normally would do
which is usually a form of judgment and
so it to have that stance of listening
for positive intent I think it changes
our own physiology I think there's a
softening and an opening and the
listening changes our body state which
is one of the things we keep wanting to
track as we talk here you know how the
body changes and because when you talk
about how when you know when we're
eating each other right we know I know
who you are
everything narrows and I think that's
where the judge just says I know what's
happening I know what I think about it I
don't like it so when you when you're
when you're you exercising your leg
that's what's really cool about circling
is it's a practice it's a it's a chance
to practice these kinds of relational
asanas yes such that when you walk on a
circling and you're not thinking about
circling when that person says that
thing to you you find yourself just
naturally more open tuned way right
without having to think about it and so
you could say this circling are almost
like you could say in speaking in this
journey if we connected to attachment
theory our ways of our postures or
relational asanas that fosters something
like secure attachment that we can
practice in extreme ways yeah so that
you can walk out there and talk to
everybody like you're in a circle but
such that you're embodied response
becomes a lot more integrated and more
open to something like having more a
secure base in your life that the people
around you that's what I'm imagining and
you know there's this phrase that oh my
gosh I'm mixing up Oh Daniel Seagle
first you and I know I think he was
referring to somebody else who coined
this concept of states into traits and
so I imagine that we're practicing
States those are the asanas and then
when you the more every every new habit
changing a habit requires repetition so
that's why having a place to practice
over and over and over and it's new
every time which is what was that called
in training where you don't do the same
thing every time
I'm like CrossFit or I don't know what
you know I'm just getting into that
myself but I forgot the term where are
you yeah you have to surprise your body
and shock your body that part yes so
it's like that every circling drop at
night is different different people
different people get circled that you
feel differently it's always different
so it is edgy it can be edging a lot of
ways but if you're committed to the
practice you start to realize there's
this enduring overall benefit you know
so in practicing you get to make
mistakes you have liberties to make
mistakes and it's encouraged yeah work
through those mistakes that like that if
you were to do the same thing and you're
in your real life it could have
consequences that are too risky yes but
so that's part of the safety is a huge
part huge where people come in and say
am i doing it wrong how do I do it right
and I really relate to that you know of
course we want to be have a general idea
or am i doing am I in the ballpark right
but I like it when you keep reminding
people it's okay to make mistakes just
do just say what you're gonna say and be
open to being coached you know or just
you know reflected to if if you're
really missing the mark you're giving
advice you know if you're judging just
owning the experience because like you
said we in our life there are
consequences for making mistakes and
people you know get can many people
might be overly cautious and that just
becomes a way of being of not all of
that experience that isn't is not even
allowed to be expressed we don't we
don't get angry or we don't love or you
know or we don't cry like these are this
is again a this is where circling to me
an attachment theory are just totally
paralleling because we're talking about
the same thing about waking up these
parts of ourselves that were not allowed
in our adult life to expressed and
having a place where we can practice a
little bit and it's like the child
learning to walk you have to do it from
the inside you can't just be told like
watching this video we're telling you
you Liss
audience what the parts are but until
we're each doing it ourselves we have
you know we have to work those edges
from the inside right yeah so yeah you
can so you can read the next one which
is we listen for how things make sense
and you can see that that's written
about in the book the survey again
second we must respond to the underlying
intentions feelings and beliefs that are
the context within which our parents our
patients words and behaviors can be seen
to make sense with bonding in this way
in light of the quote intentional stance
unquote of our patients allows them to
feel understood in depth and this
translates into a feeling of being
accepted feeling understood and accepted
fosters confidence that their
experiences even those they have know
that they have had no have had to bury
can be safely contained in the new
attachment relationship so what did you
get from that paragraph well they will
be experiences so one of the things that
we say encircling is how do you know
when you feel gotten you know what tells
you when when you feel hurt listen to or
understood you know or gotten or have
another term that we use as shared
reality like I know that we have shared
reality that you understood what I just
said or you just you understood me right
even more precise you understood me is
that your criteria is like and I got
this from Mark Lewis thinking deeply
influenced circling we was already happy
inside a circling so a lot of his really
interesting shion's continue to live on
shout out to mark these awesome like a
fact we we do these we i saw your a
recently yeah
one coming up nice soon that the
criteria of how I know that is is is
that when I share and then you respond
to me in such a way that the end of your
response I end up feeling understood and
accepted mm-hmm and I think that there's
that those are two distinctive things
and they can that that I could I
definitely had the experience of feeling
understood but not accepted we had that
experience right and I've definitely had
the experience to of feeling accepted
but not necessarily like you heard me or
you understood me mm-hmm
nice I like that you're making that
distinction it's like that like the
acceptance it's like cool like yeah I do
I feel like you love me accept me can
use human being but I so don't feel
understood and I was just complete so
until you I go but once you add in the
thumb the understanding is like always
been just absolutely fascinating why
when I say something and you and you and
you let me know that you understand what
I just heard how I know he's not a
thought I know because I go like this
what is that and I think that has
something to do with the the word like
oh I get that like I get that you get
that I make sense and I make sense to
you right because I make sense to you
then that validates my own way of making
sense to myself and that's that term
making sense
right cuz usually think about making
sense as I think about like I'm trying
to figure something out mentally and
maybe that's the way that it ends up
happening but the moment I get it it
drops into a sensation making sense
sensation wow that's a I like that one
that's I like that form
low case thought about the other day
nice nice um so just to repeat what you
said because this is also what I was
highlighting in this quote is getting
the others intentional stance
well first you listen for how it makes
sense and then you're getting there
intentional stance it equals
understanding it equals a feeling I mean
like you're saying it they don't have to
follow each other but that's what we're
aiming for encircling we're finding ways
and one way it works is because I think
we have multiple people in a circle
reflecting different things and so I'll
often not see a lot of things and then
somebody will say something that I just
love how they where did they get that
from but then I'm able to see you know
it's just we keep waking each other up
as a group it's not just again that
one-to-one relationship a therapist and
client which is and I'm not putting it
down I'm just wanting to say that these
you know because there's a lot you don't
get encircling that you can get in
therapy let's just say that so but when
we get the understanding the acceptance
then the phrase here is increased
confidence like you're saying that our
experiences are safely contained in the
new attachment relationship and again my
query is is that phrase is that
happening as a surrogate attachment
relationship in the field so so I'm just
looking for all the ways that you know I
don't want to I don't want to force the
theory I want it to be illuminated and I
think that will happen by people
responding and if there's concerns or
doubts or questions you know that we can
as a community yeah really
there's something here this this thing
about like making sense to well there's
you know one of the things that there's
in teaching people how to circle right
you know a lot of it is actually you
know opening up it one to circle you bet
you have to do with your whole be right
if you have a relationship it it's
really done with the whole being right
and there's this landings over the years
that his
articulated out of circling cuz that's
how that's how circling has come to
being as I think I was like good
therapies coming in to be anything
anything involving you know knowledge
that becomes words and then reiterated
in practice and like a thing at first it
doesn't arise in the mind does an idea
or a theory either then somebody creates
a method no it's enacted in the body and
acted out to first right it's like there
was a knowledge that was lived from the
bottom up in your behavior first and
that's so important I think what he's
he's talking a lot about is that the
that so much of the base level of
relationship has to do with actually
you're more like your ear um your your
motor sister sensory motor sis yes yes
race to this so for example right now
with you and I you're shaking your head
yes just in there smiling in recognition
and I'm smiling in and there's this
whole level of this very intricate
subtle coordinated thing going on that
if all of a sudden I were just to be
like I'm talking to you and all of a
sudden I were to be like like um right
or if I laughed at the wrong time or I
or I went outside of the range of the
dance it would be like something broke
wouldn't have the attunement yes we lose
a tournament so kuehnemund
has a lot to do with coordination
there's a lot to do with joining in it
like like in a dirted Rena that feeling
into at a bodily level yes well there's
yeah you want to and so it so it's like
you know as we learn how to do circling
and we started to understand well when
people have these epic moments of
feeling deeply gotten what are how does
that happen and one of the big reasons
that that happen is we've teased out is
like actually that one is that you know
in a Heidegger and in the existential
phenomenologist talked a lot about this
is the
you could say that you could almost say
that the human being is that part of the
cosmos that makes sense of the cosmos
mm-hmm it's the most vulnerable self
transparent to itself opening such that
it makes sense of its world we are
almost indistinguishable from a sense
making and so another way of saying that
is my experience always makes sense in
other words as an internal logic to it
and so when you make sense to me what
you're doing is that when you make sense
to me it means that I'm and I
demonstrate that you make sense you may
show it to you like I let you know yeah
actually letting you know is that like I
see the logic or the logos of your
experience how you make sense of your
world it's valid
it's called validity right so when when
when I validate what I when I validate
you what I'm really saying is I'm
validating the logic upon which you're
experiencing folds and I understand it
and of course that makes sense to me
because if this is important to you and
then they said this of course that how
are you gonna feel of course you course
you feel that way fact I feel that way
just listening to you and then there's a
free a term called cross modal
responsiveness I'm talking about the
parent that's the sexy Freight crap
responsible use that everybody use it on
your first day well it's in what I hear
you saying and and it's it contributes
to this Bray's feeling felt which they
which is referenced in the book this
idea of feeling felt that we often use
that phrase in circling but cross modal
responsiveness is in the between the
parent and the child where the parent
responds let's see what pages is on
because I didn't write down the page for
this one sorry but the parent responds
in a different sensory register
and that there's a response to the
emotional experience but it's there's
something that the way it shareable is
you're not mimicking what a person is
doing like you're describing you're
feeling it in yourself and you respond
as you would respond to that person and
it's there's a share that's there where
something shared yeah they give an
example of the child squeeze
squeals with joy and her mother's body
answers with a response of shimmy and it
says he says it allows the child to feel
known and without it she may only feel
imitated and so the idea here that I
will get into as we just go along I'm
gonna try to let go of it so much into
really that strikes me right there so
like you said something and I feel
struck right now you should go lucky
she's a bit we can go you should go yeah
I feel and then I feel mimicked by you
but I don't feel responded to by you
right so this difference between being
feeling mimicked or being mimicked and
being responded to what I'm hearing you
say is it has to do with when I mimic
you I'm not really including myself yes
it's when I respond to you is when I
have my own genuine spontaneous response
directly to you which means implicitly
seems like I had skin in the game you
see me implicitly in my unique response
right to your unique response and I
would imagine that one on a base level
it it's a confirming way to response I'm
basically saying that like your
communication to me was legitimate
enough for me to elicit myself being
affected
I think that's really important and it's
for me it's an edge encircling take you
just responded to that you felt my cross
modeled with you yeah and I want to
share that that's just something
encircling that is an edge for me that I
wish I could practice more you know that
I want to practice more waking up direct
responsiveness letting it be more varied
right more from more depth more richness
not just a habitual way of responding to
somebody like okay here I'm showing you
some compassion or here I'm showing you
you know I'm res Here I am resonating
with you but how do you actually access
those shared response like you're saying
okay I see you kind of a personal
question about that
sure yeah so does it so basically what
you're saying is is that one of the
things that you notice that like it's an
edge for you and that you want to like
owning more on is is is registering more
of a sense of responsiveness to the
other in your in your sessions and with
people that whatever you say yeah I mean
I would be surprised if my clients said
I don't already do that you know I mean
I think in my work I do it and they're
good enough I would say but but yet I'm
aware that personally yeah in fact I can
put it this way that in my work a
certain field is developed I'm in the
role something really opens and comes
alive for me you know similar to these
videos you know where I'm really focused
on you what we're talking about I'm
feeling a lot as we're talking yeah but
other times when I'm not in the role
that's where something can get more
quiet and maybe a little distant you
know and so I'm interested in catching
these that kind of natural response and
growing it
right that makes sense yeah it doesn't
make sense anything I'm curious about
does that make sense to you that that
there's ways in which you want to be
more responsive that you don't always
have access to and then you're working
on like is that does that Conte is that
does that link back for you like with
your mom or your family or like does
that make sense that that would be well
I think you know the answers to that but
yes yes you know all about my mom and my
family and you know I I appreciate you
asking that because it's you know yeah
it's I think it's appropriate to bring
specific personal examples into these
explorations and so I think that there
has become you know I think I actually
think I was more anxious when I was
younger but I'm curious but I perceive
myself as having got has I became more
avoidant in some ways and so when when I
started studying this I caught that and
I started to see how can I I learned
that avoidant attachment is has to do
with the suppression of feeling and you
know on a regular basis and in real in
within intimacy the person who's
avoidant lis attached conceal all kinds
of feelings by themself or with somebody
that there's no skin in the game like
you're saying yeah and this might be
generalizing but I think it's an
important way to just to consider it and
what happens when you're just meeting
another human being and what's your
natural response without trying totally
like see I think that's so important I
because I've just watched this
encircling that there's so you know just
watching how deeply self-regulating when
people share and they look up and they
see a bunch of people coordinating
movements in direct response to their
utterance right you could see this
warmth in
this kind of human feeling just come
over them as they as that coordination
happens right and so I would imagine
that like if it's so confirming right
it's so confirming Morris Berman has
this this notion about that he thinks
that the disconnection from our somatic
being has to do with these experiencing
extreme versions and or chronic versions
of what he would kit would say is a dis
come for me disconfirming ways of being
responded to yes yeah
exactly because if you think about it
when you when you elicit a communication
it arises from the legitimacy of a
little self legitimacy of your
personhood and so somebody like hears
you but then doesn't respond to anything
that you said and kind of veers off at a
glance right so if you're like mom I
need I'm hungry and she goes like look
at the pink flowers over there that I'm
gonna do that right in that moment
there's this kind of break and I think
we've all experienced this this is kind
of there's this weird awkward break
right that kind of you could say it's
creates a schism between the self in the
other yes and in that moment right
there's this kind of like um who's it
calls he calls it the basic fault right
this schism between the self and the
other where what ends up happening is
that you lose grounding and in the in
the somatic flow in feeling of being a
body and you rise up and you become you
start to identify yourself as an other
for others right which is an attempt to
heal the fault line or the schism
between this element like how you're
saying that and I felt really sad
feeling into that imagining myself or
anyone else having that experience where
you have to associate from your body
self the flow of experience become a
self for others but I like that phrase
he'll default
this isn't yeah and he says that to the
degree that yourself is Wow I'm just
whoa - just took that in another level
okay I mean it just it sort of just
keeps coming through me and that's
listening right there stop the other
person from talking to say I'm still
taking it in it's still wait it's still
affecting me see I feel really heard
I feel really connected to you and I
feel like a sense of expansion or
inspiration or excitement feels really
alive and I just wish that our whole
world could learn that it's not just
about listening and holding space and
not including ourselves that's something
I just love having learned in the
community here is that each of our
experience matters when I'm talking if
I'm being circled your experience
matters what's happening over there
I mean it's so dynamic you know right
and it will just deepen that just a
little bit and complete that loop you
know I think that that what would burrow
say would be something like so we we
lose connection with their somatic
grounding of being a body and we in
those weird awkward disconfirming
responses we kind of like break from it
and then start to become an other for
others right it could be you could use
that word fawning right where somebody's
just yeah just paying a tenth like maybe
it's a hovering or smothering but
instead when both people's experiences
matter you know when somebody could say
you know I love what you're saying but
I'm getting tired I just need to pause
for nobody can ever say that when does
that happen
can we pause for a moment and just be
here I mean and there's I think that I
think you brilliantly just brought it
back to what he would say that he's like
okay if you want to know to what degree
that yourself has been confiscated this
is this is I you know is to what degree
are
comfortable being in the presence of
other people and being in silence beer
Morris Berman would say any wrote I
think this has come from the book coming
to her since it's by Morris permit the
brilliant book brilliant book about this
we I think what he would say would be
that to the degree that you're
comfortable in silence
around other people write these two
degree that you're grounded in the
semantic reality of your body health and
other but this I did want to say
something particular which is that it -
what's circling invites for both of
these attachment styles is for the
preoccupied anxious that's more it the
idea is under stress that the attention
goes more to the other and so circling
invites the preoccupied to feel
themselves slow down feel yourself more
include your experience and for the
avoidant Lee attached if they get to
circling because they do want to be in
relationship you know a kid because they
can even not want to participate I don't
know I mean that might be extreme but
the avoidant Lee attached can sit back
and feel not be pressured to participate
and just be in the field and there's no
obligation to answer anything in
particular but the invitation to study
their own experience and participate as
they want to so you know but so we come
over to this side and you know do
different things that start to shift
that start to get through in some way I
imagine right touches on parts over here
starts to wake up and engage and and
then shift the energy down here oh yes
working you need some more of that
okay good okay so yeah well what if I
just named these two other parts and
then when we put the video up I'm gonna
I'm just gonna put the quotes and things
that I wanted to read yes people can
just read them and then we can go on to
mentalization next time so hmm
so feeling felts is an important part
there's also something called upgrading
the dialog and then there's something
else called scaffolding and when I read
this part about upgrading the dialog I
thought that's inherently what you have
been showing me in reflection at least
all these years I've known you the the
quote is that Bromberg describes
psychotherapy as a process that as
patients to change while staying the
same so we do that in circling circulars
to change while staying the same along
the same lines Friedman suggests that we
as therapists need to accept our
patients or fellow circulars on their
own terms while also refusing to settle
for those terms striking this kind of
balance requires us to assume that our
patients fellow circulars are capable of
somewhat more feeling thoughtfulness
connection or initiative than they
believe they are expect too little and
the patient or circular feel his hopes
have been betrayed expect too much and
the patient or circular may feel his
vulnerabilities have gone unrecognized
and so I think that's exactly the level
we're working at where the depth of
which we strive to accept what is and
then yet we're seeing each we're seeing
parts of each other
that may that we don't fully see yet you
know see you reflect what you're hearing
and you add something to it and I feel
unexpectedly different you know
I think that you were doing that in the
beginning of the video I'd say you were
upgrading the dialogue for myself you
know where you're reflecting to me what
you seen in me in this whole process and
then there's scaffolding hmm where we're
trying on the others experience which is
what we're always doing upgrading the
dialogue to higher levels of awareness
and complexity right requires what
developmentalists call scaffolding so
parents for example scaffold their
child's emerging capacity for language
by speaking for her before she acquires
the word to describe her experience and
later by asking her to use your words
these two quotes are on page 198 and I
think scaffolding is one of your
specialties and I wanted to know if you
knew that phrase or if you see what I'm
saying if you recognize that yeah I mean
I definitely recognize what you're
talking about scaffolding do you know
why why that metaphor is you scaffolding
is it so sometimes you speak for the
other it's again on 1 198 and you're
articulating the unarticulated and
unrecognized feelings and some to other
times
receptive silence is called for to make
room for the person the patient circular
to feel or feel more deeply and at
certain moments we may need to bridge
the dialogue to a more emotional level
by going first and expressing our own
feelings so yeah this has happened where
you'll start to say something if I'm you
know at an impasse you'll start to talk
and it'll wake something up in me well
the wind is coming speaking of waking
you up yes I think I do get what you're
saying in the sense of of that
there is in listening to you one of the
things I've been because we're doing the
Explorer weekend coming up all right
it it's all about attunement this one
this particular was all about deep
attunements and like things like deeply
listening and really kind of getting
that all the way into our own being and
practicing that developing that part of
ourselves and
there is it's so it's so interesting how
deep this one goes right like when I
listen with my whole being it's the
thing that struck me is that there's the
problem the problem with being a
speaking being is I only have one mouth
you know I have two years I have two
eyes you know I do everything but I'll
have one mouth that's such a bummer I
think I've never heard anybody say that
I don't think cuz I have one mouth and
makes speaking fundamentally really
different than listening cuz like when I
speak I can only speak one word at a
time one sentence at a time or that I
get scattered so listening is not linear
it's holographic well I see everything
in there and that's why it's important
and this is why it's important to really
educate your listening because the more
educated your listening is the more
distinctions that you have the more that
you can hear right what somebody's
saying because you're holding all of
that knowledge or those distinctions at
once so it'd be a kind of like a thing
where you say X Y & Z and what I hear in
between x and y is a whole other
alphabet right and it's not like you
don't know that that's true you main
didn't know that you knew that that was
true
um but you could only say what you're
saying but because I'm attuned to you
and and if by listening is really like
really attuned and educated and the more
distinctions I have the more I can see
and respond to error phrase or reflect
right not only what you said but like
what you didn't say and what you didn't
know that you didn't say and that you
didn't know that you knew which in a
certain sense is upgrading the
conversation because like you're
bringing your linear kind of struggle to
talk about make sense of yourself and it
it happens inside of a vat of like one
care right and then and then - I can I
can receive all of the verbal and
nonverbal communications and here in
between the things that you're saying
and then I can bring all that in some
way back to you and then it's in
some way it's more whole what you said
is like you what what you send out what
is true comes back to you more hole and
I think that wholeness is felt by like
this like the experience of being gotten
like I love that you keep putting in a
body response yeah you know and so that
that's what we started with at the
beginning and you you made that gesture
towards the beginning and and that that
being the signal that you're being
gotten that you're feeling felt only
what I'm really appreciating about this
is like I think the most important thing
is that we're in a real dialogue so it's
kind of like it's kind of like I love
personally that we're not getting
everything and they were going on I'm
having ideas and they're alive and
you're having responses to my ideas and
having ideas that are alive and I think
what that is is like that's the that's
how that's how we constitute each other
in relationship is is we continually
move towards the unknown and come to
terms with things and I think what we're
inviting everyone into in listening this
conversation is to not just receive
information but think along with right
that's why we want to say put your
questions in the in the facebook chat
like let us know what you think you tell
us where you disagree right you knows
notice how how young we both look and
how amazing being with you like it is
taking about I just filled the reverb or
the atmosphere of just our connection
what's there be
I feel a buzzing in my arms and I feel I
feel a relief again of not being so
attached to all the things I wanted to
read and reference just more of being in
a space with you and I I feel confident
that enough as being where I were being
specific while actually just enjoy I
guess I really it's almost like I took a
drug and found myself just in a space
with you that I didn't know I was gonna
be in I thought it would be more
didactic and I'm surprised I feel
surprised at how interactive it bills
hmm if it wasn't didactic at what's the
would that you would describe his face
in room if it wasn't didactic yeah you
said it you thought it'd be more
didactic yeah is it moral it's fully a
effectively attuned inter subjective
cross-modal
field of caregiving surveys safe-haven
Grand Slam I feel exactly as I feel so
cross-modal and effectively attuned yeah
yes yeah I feel very similar it was a um
yeah I feel there's a fullness there's a
relaxation there's a light heartedness
and and and a depth and and I think
mostly I think a lot of that has to do
with just I love it when you get nervous
because I and I think what I don't I
don't I get that it's not pleasant being
nervous but like that's not what I love
is that you you know no I know you mean
I appreciate that I feel safe being
nervous with you and one way I'm just
talking to you know well I think what it
taps into me is like it's it's you're
nervous because you care about something
and like that's what I always feel when
you're nervous they'll think oh my god
something's really important to you I
felt I felt closer to that and including
this closer to you now
inquisitive dude oh thank you guys
Thank You Monica love you should be
continued
oh yeah don't go away